http://youtu.be/xpiamDPXQrI
khang_vgu
PROFESSOR: Let's tie all of these together with something practical.
bây giờ ta đút kết những điều vừa rồi bằng thứ thực tiễn
All of you know what a battery is.
đó là pin
A battery in your cell phone runs the loads that your phone requires,
pin giúp điện thoại hoạt động, liên lạc...
whether it is communication, the phone activity, whatever it might be.
...
So we can think of your phone or any other system that has a battery as a--
ta có thể xem xét đến điện thoại, hoặc những hệ thống khác có pin
this is my symbol for a battery.
đây là kí hiệu cho pin
And let's say we have a 9-volt battery.
ta có một cục pin 9 Volt
And we look at the battery as being a chemical device with terminals.
cục pin có thể xem như thiết bị hóa học với các cực
And we say there are positive and negative terminals.
ở đây có những cực âm và cực dương
And whatever your system is built off can be abstracted as a load, we are
bất cứ hệ thống nào được dựng lên, đều có thể xem như là một tải,
representing the load as a resistance, R. So when we subject our battery to
ta biểu diễn tải như một điện trở R, khi ta kết hợp pin với tại lại
this load and we typically will have an on/off switch or some kind, maybe.
ta cần công tắc đóng/mở hoặc loại khác tương tự
And maybe I'll have an on/off switch of some kind.
...
So when I turn this switch on--
khi ta mở công tắc này--
OK, when the switch is closed, this will cause a current to flow across
khi đóng nó lại, dòng điện sẽ chạy qua
the load that will power the function of your system, whether it's a cell
tải sẽ cấp năng lượng cho chức năng của hệ thống
phone or any other device.
bất kể nó là pin, điện thoại hay cái khác
Now we have the equation that we saw before, which is energy is equal to
ở đây, ta có công thức từ những phần trước
power times time.
công = năng lượng x thời gian
So I'm going to write that as E equals P times time.
viết tắt là E = P x t
But we also know power, P, is given by V times I. So I can write this as V
và như đã biết, P = V x I nên ta có thể viết E thành
times I times time.
E = V x I x t
So when we have a battery, the battery has a fixed amount of energy.
với một cục pin, nó sẽ có một lượng công nhất định
So this is fixed.
nó là cố định
And one of the properties of a battery is it provides a constant voltage.
một trong những đặc tính của pin là nó cung cấp một điện áp không đổi
This is also fixed.
nó cũng cố định
So this equation tells us is that, if I want the battery to last for a long
vậy công thức này chỉ rằng, nếu ta muốn pin hoạt động cho quãng thời gian dài
amount of time, the only thing I can control is the current.
thứ duy nhất có thể làm là điều chỉnh dòng điện
This is the control.
đây là bộ điều khiển
So I have these two in my control, so I can consume less current and make it
ta có 2 cái ở đây, ta tiêu thụ dòng điện ít
last longer.
thì pin hoạt động lâu hơn
Or I can consume more current and have it last less time.
hoặc tiêu thụ dòng điện nhiều và mau hết pin
So this is a practical application of something that we've
đây là ứng dụng thực tế
already looked at.
...